We will get started.
Well, temporarily leaving
the land of systems
to talk about more deep
learning stuff, which we're
going to have two lectures
on scaling law and scaling
law adjacent phenomena.
So today is going
to be the basics.
We're just going to talk about
pretty basic scaling law stuff.
Some of the classic works.
How does the basic
idea of scaling laws
connect to maybe things you know
about from machine learning 101.
And then in two
lectures, we're going
to do the more advanced
version of the scaling laws
lecture, where we're
going to basically go
into a bunch of modern, open
model tech reports, things
like mu p and other
parameter initializations,
and this year I'm going
to throw in some more
stuff for optimizers.
So there will be
an advanced version
of this that will try to
really get to the cutting edge.
Today, we're going to start
with all the really basic stuff.
And due to some
scheduling constraints,
next lecture will be
inference, so you're
going to go back and forth.
You're going to do scaling laws
and inference and then scaling
laws again.
So scaling laws is really the
following scenario in some ways,
or you run into it very quickly
once you run into this scenario.
So you have your
very wealthy friend,
who has given you 10,000
B200s for a month,
and he or she has asked you to
build a very good open source
language model.
They would like to get
something out of those B200s.
And so you've already put
together your infra team.
That's your
assignment to buddies.
And you have, let's say a
good pre-training data set.
That's going to be the
assignment after this,
but let's say you
already have that.
And then you're going to
go and train a big model,
but there's lots of choices
in training a big model-- all
the assignments, the earlier
lecture two stuff that we had
earlier, where you have
questions like what architecture
should I use?
What should my
hyperparameters be?
And it's very scary
to run these things
on a run that is
basically, potentially
millions of dollars
in cost, so how
do you really take this idea
of scaling up very seriously?
How do you make sure that your
big run is actually successful?
So of these many
choices, some of which
you're going to just copy
out of the literature.
The stuff that I talked about
earlier in the architecture
lecture is really about,
well adopted best practices,
and you will probably just pick
some of these out of a hat.
That's fine, but really, let's
say you're at the frontier.
You would like to
build something
that's actually better than the
best available models today.
You have to start
really optimizing these.
You can't just copy
the choices of others
and get something that's better
than the state of the art.
So how do we do that?
Well, that's going to
require us to really engage
with this idea of scaling.
So scaling laws have been
one very powerful tool.
You might also
call it a paradigm.
Scaling laws, if you talk to
some people who are really
in these big labs
doing scaling work,
it's almost kind
of a way of life.
They're like, we really
believe in the scaling laws.
It's almost a belief,
and you'll see
why scaling laws can sometimes
be quite tricky objects.
But really, scaling laws are
these simple, predictive rules
of how to go from small scale
model performance and behavior,
and to try to extrapolate them
up to large scale behavior.
And so the basic naive way
to approach model training
might be to say, I
have a big budget,
I'm going to do multiple
training runs on these very
big runs, and I'm going
to tune hyperparameters
on those big runs, but
that's very wasteful.
So instead, what
I would like to do
is I would like to do all of my
optimization at the small scale
and have some simple
rule that allows
me to extrapolate small scale
behaviors to large scale
behaviors.
And if the small
scale and large scale
are connected by some very
simple, robust connections
like regularities of
some kind, then you
would have confidence in this
kind of new scaling approach
to optimizing your system.
And that's really
what today is all
going to be about-- this
engineering view of a scaling
law.
And to start with, I'm
going to talk a little bit
about background, because
scaling laws are very
interesting in that not only are
they the newest paradigm, that's
how a lot of these models
are designed and thought,
but also they connect very
closely to very classical ideas.
So if you're a person that's
a machine learning theorist,
actually, there are some
things that you will really
feel at home with in some ways,
so they're like empirical sample
complexities.
And then I'll talk through the
history of scaling laws of one
kind and show you that this is
not something that's really new.
It's something with actually
quite a bit of history
and research done to it.
So I really, really had to
put some math into my slides.
I really feel the
need to do so, but one
of the things that
is very interesting
is that for the longest
time, machine learning
has thought about this question
of how will my model perform,
especially from a
theory perspective?
I have this model class, how
good is my model going to be?
And generalization bound
is the theorists answer
to this question, so
you have your error,
over some finite
hypothesis class,
and you say, oh,
my error is going
to be at most this much
worse than the model's
performance on my training set.
This is classic
generalization bounds.
You can write this down
for more complex classes
like smooth densities
or whatever,
but importantly,
not only does this
tell you some of
performance, notice
that these bounds are often
dependent on the sample size.
And so this is telling
you, well, this
is a theoretical upper
bound on my loss values
as a function of how
my training set grows.
And in some ways, that's very
closely related to this idea
of what happens as I scale up
the amount of data that I have?
Those are closely
related questions,
where you might believe
me that that's true.
And if you try to figure out
what is the very first scaling
law paper that exists?
It turns out you can
go back quite far.
You can go back to Bell Labs
and Corina Cortez and Vladimir
Vapnik and these folks that
were doing very serious theory
work on machine learning,
ask this question, well,
training classifiers on
a really large data set
is often very expensive.
We would like to
avoid doing that,
and to do so maybe we can just
fit classifiers on a smaller
sample, fit a curve to how
their error rates decay,
and use that as a way to
estimate their performance.
That's almost literally a
data scaling law back in 1993.
So this idea, at the
very least, thinking
about how your
model's performance
changes as a function of
data set size is just a very
classical one, and
there's a lot of work that
supports this kind of idea.
I just want to connect this
to some of these older ideas
so you don't really think
of scaling laws as this very
new, purely neural thing.
It's an idea that has a lot
of roots in empirical machine
learning, and also connections
to theoretical machine learning.
And if you start to look
at the history of this,
there's a lot of people that
have said, isn't it the case
that maybe instead of spending
money on algorithm development,
maybe we should just
go collect more data,
because if we plot how the
performance of our systems
behave as a function of the
amount of data that we have,
it turns out that they are
all increasing or improving
in predictable ways?
Banko and Brill, is one of the
canonical NLP references in how
the amount of data and
thinking about scaling
is a really valid way of
improving system performance,
so there's lots of ways
of thinking about this.
And there's also work
by other NLP folks
like Kolachina et al. in 2012.
This is one of the earlier
works on different kinds
of functional forms for scaling
laws, where once again, they're
increasing the amount of data
that they're using to train.
In this case, machine
translation systems or BLEU
scores.
And they're asking like, what
is the right functional form
for how a model's
performance behaves
as a function of
increased data amount?
And they maybe surprisingly
or not surprisingly,
end up with the same power laws,
which is pow 3 and 4 as really
we do today.
For the rest of
the lecture, you're
going to keep seeing essentially
these polynomial functions, pow
3 and pow 4 as I talk
about scaling laws.
And we knew about a lot
of this back in the 2010's
that these kinds
of functional forms
were very predictive of model
behavior as we scaled them up.
And then finally, I really like
mentioning this paper because
for whatever reason,
they don't get,
or Hestness et al.
don't get cited
quite as much as they should.
The origins of neural
scaling, I would point back
to Hestness in 2017.
Really a very
forward looking work
in many ways that
built these scaling
laws as a function
of data set size
for a wide variety of systems,
different kinds of speech
recognition systems, machine
translation systems, language
models, and they showed
that these things follow
these nice polynomial trends
across a really large number
of domains.
And it was really
ahead of its time,
because 2017 was long before
some of the earlier OpenAI
scaling laws and
so on in the 2020s.
And they talked about stuff
that we talk about today,
like emergence,
where suddenly models
might show certain
kinds of capabilities
because accuracy is a much
more discontinuous measure
than losses.
And really, scaling by compute,
that if we have systems
that scale predictably to
large training data, then
really compute is going
to be really important.
And then finally, since we're
scaling by compute, well,
speed and systems optimization
is going to turn into accuracy.
So in some ways, a lot of
the things that we see today,
like the phenomena of
system scaling and so on,
we could have really known,
or I could have known in 2017
had I read and thought about a
lot of these scaling laws papers
back and thought about
them more seriously.
So to mention that paper in
every one of these scaling law
lectures I give, just to
say, a lot of these phenomena
were known far before
the modern era,
or the Modern Language
modeling era in that it's
possible to have known
the regime that we're
in even before seeing these
large language models.
That's very cool to know.
Any questions about this
semi-historical part?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE], and I'm
wondering if those are just
stored empirically, or
is there some way we
can justify all of this?
You're asking about
these scaling laws,
and where they come from?
These are pure curve
fitting exercises.
I will talk a little bit about
where scaling laws can come from
and why polynomials are arguably
a very natural class of scaling
laws, but there's no golden rule
that these are the only ones.
I will say, though,
that in some ways,
theory provides a very rich
place, where the scaling law
functional forms can
come from because theory
is often thinking a lot about
how do error rates decay
as a function of
various objects?
And they give you
candidate functional forms
of various kinds.
Physicists are also
very good at this
because they thinking
about limits,
like how do the limits behave?
And that gives you different
scaling law functional forms.
Cool.
All right, any other questions?
Good.
So now I'm going to start
talking about more modern neural
language model
scaling, and I'm going
to start with data scaling laws
because to me, they're the most
simple and natural objects.
Talking about data
scaling laws also
allows me to walk you through
very step-by-step on how
we might guess what the
functional form of a scaling law
might be and why the polynomial
form is a natural one.
And then I'm going to start
talking about hyper parameters
and architectures and all sorts
of other more exotic objects
that are going to be harder
to justify from intuition,
but still turn out to have very
nice scaling law behaviors.
One of the things that's
remarkable about this scaling
law style analysis has been that
these power law relationships
seem to hold for a huge
variety of different factors.
So the basic ones that
we see in pre-training,
and those are going to
be the ones that I'm
going to talk about today.
The usual ones that you see
are compute on the x-axis.
This is log compute.
Sorry, on the x-axis, log
of test loss on the y-axis,
or log of the data
set on x-axis,
log of loss on the
y-axis, log of parameters
on x-axis, log of loss,
once again, on the y-axis.
So we can get a variety
of different x-axes
that you might think of as
resources in the log axis.
All of them linearize
log test loss here.
You can see also much
more exotic scaling laws.
You can see scaling
laws that are basically
the equivalent to these
in downstream benchmarks.
In those cases, you expect to
see a sigmoid functional form
as a function of compute
or compute-like quantities.
There's even been many
works recently, more
on the forecasting side,
where people are doing things
like putting dates
as the x-axis.
And strangely enough,
at least for these
plots-- like the upper
envelope of these curves
are often linear in various
forms of capabilities.
There's no reason that
on this bottom side,
the more exotic scaling
laws need to be true.
But it turns out to be the case
that I guess language model
performance is often much more
regular as a function of scale
and resources than it
initially might appear.
So to begin with, I'm going to
start with data scaling laws.
And data scaling laws
are a very simple kind
of univariate relationship that
we're going to think about.
So in this world, we're going
to fix our model training
procedure.
And in general, unless
I say otherwise,
the models are going
to generally be
bigger than the data set size.
And I'm going to increase my
data set size in a regular way,
and I'm going to see
how the error reduces.
And what do we expect
out of this relationship?
In general, it's going
to be monotone-ish
if we tune our
hyperparameters well.
Because we have
more data, more data
should help us do
better at our task.
The error should decrease.
And if you're doing something
like classification, or even
for next token prediction,
you should really
go from random guessing to
some of entropy-like object
where you can't do any better
than the irreducible error
of your task.
That's the noise floor.
So we're going to have some
sigmoidal-like object over here.
So this is generally what
we expect out of our system.
So we're going to start with
an empirical observation,
and should make
this on your own.
You'll make something
that looks roughly
like this in parts
of assignment 3,
which is if we just
have a very big model,
much bigger than
our data set, and we
increase the data set size, and
we put that on the log axis,
and on the y-axis, we
have log test loss.
Once again, you will find that
the two points that you plot
will form a very
clear linear trend.
I've taken this
from Kaplan in 2020.
I'm going to refer
repeatedly to this paper.
This one's OpenAI's "Neural
Scaling Laws" paper.
They have a lot of
lovely ablations
and a lot of lovely data.
Now, this relationship,
where I've
plotted a line on
a log-log plot,
this is a scale-free or
power law relationship.
And what does that mean?
If I have a line
on a log-log plot?
Many of you-- to many of you,
this is probably obvious.
But just to really
emphasize this,
if something is linear
in a log-log plot, what
does that mean?
Well, it means that
the error that I have
is decaying polynomially.
And also, it usually means
that I'm very far away
from my asymptote.
Because once I
approach my asymptote,
I'm going to taper off
rather than have a line.
So let's go through an
example just to show you
how scaling law arises
very naturally on a very
simple estimation problem.
So forget language
modeling for the moment.
This was a language
modeling class,
but now it is a statistics
class for the next one
slide or actually two slides.
No, maybe three slides.
So in this case,
what I want to do
is I want to estimate the
mean from a bunch of data.
And so I have an input,
it's drawn from a Gaussian.
And I'm going to estimate
the mean of this object.
I just write down
the empirical mean.
And then, you can write
down what the error is.
So what's the expected error?
Well, each of these
guys is Gaussian,
and that the mu hat is Gaussian,
so I can write down the error.
That's going to be
sigma squared over n.
So well, if you look at
this, is a scaling law.
I've written down the error,
and the error, if I log that,
is a function of log n,
log n being the log x-axis.
So in general, if
you can come up
with anything that
is essentially
1 over n to the alpha
plus some constant,
when you plot that
on a log-log plot,
subtracting out
the constant term,
you're going to
get a scaling log.
So anything of this form,
where you have polynomial decay
and errors, is going to end
up giving you a scaling law.
And of course, in parametric
estimation like mean estimation
or regression, you of course,
expect a polynomial rate.
You don't really
expect anything else.
And if you've taken your
stats estimation courses,
you know that essentially
all the classical
models you are expected to
have a 1 over n scaling.
If you fit a regression or
so on, you might get D over n
or whatever else.
And so if this is true, and this
is the origins of scaling laws,
if we plot our lines,
we should expect
to see roughly a
slope of minus 1
because that's the
exponent on the x.
Y equals minus x plus C.
If we fit our
neural scaling laws,
we will find that our
exponents are quite different.
These exponents-- I've
taken from these two
on the left from Hestenes,
I've taken the one on the right
from Kaplan.
They're about -0.1, -0.3,
-0.1, roughly speaking.
And so what does that mean?
That means this is much
slower than estimating a mean
or estimating a
linear regression.
So this is much, much slower
convergence rate, still
polynomial, but much slower.
Now this is interesting.
It's saying that we're
getting these kind
of nice polynomial rates, but
the exponents are not so great.
They're -0.1.
Where might you get an
estimation rate like this?
Well, you would get this if your
model was more nonparametric.
I promise this will
be the last statistics
slide of this lecture.
Let's say that I
want to estimate now,
instead of a mean, an
arbitrary smooth function.
So one thing I could do is, if
I'm doing a regression problem,
I have my inputs, x1 through xn.
Let's say they're
in the unit box.
I have a little bit
of Gaussian noise,
and I have an unknown function
f that I would like to estimate.
A trivial estimator for
this is I can take my space,
I can cut it up into
little 2D boxes of length n
to the negative 1 to the fourth.
And then what's our
estimation error?
I'll have square root n boxes.
Each box is going to get
square root n samples.
And the error is
going to be roughly 1
over square root
of n or something.
And in general, if have
a D-dimensional function
I would like to estimate in this
very nonparametric, arbitrary
way, my error is going
to be roughly equal to n
to the negative 1 over d.
So my scaling is going
to be y equals negative 1
over D times x.
And so now these kinds more
flexible functions, functions
that are more flexible
than the linear class,
now have rates in their scaling
laws that are not just 1,
they're 1 over D.
And so one mental model
that you could have
is that the neural networks I
was showing you in these slides
are behaving kind of
non-parametric regressors in 10
dimensions, like a nearest
neighbor or other kinds
of estimators in 10 dimensions.
That's roughly the rate at
which they learn from data.
That's kind of a
cool thing to be
able to know just by looking
at some of these scaling laws.
Some people have argued
this more strongly.
Bari et al. and some other
scaling law theory folks
have argued that the scaling
law exponents are actually
literally telling us
that the neural network
is behaving like a
non-parametric smoother,
and so on and so forth.
It's an interesting
set of arguments,
and you can by that intuition
to whatever extent you'd like.
I don't quite how much I
truly, truly buy this argument.
There's some of the evidence
that might be a little sketchy.
It relies on estimators
of intrinsic dimension,
but it's an interesting
thing to think about
that somehow these
exponents are telling us
how fast are these neural
networks really learning.
OK, so actually, I'll
pause for the moment here.
That's really the end of the
really basic data scaling
law of one distribution,
and you sample from it,
and you learn from it.
Is that all clear, like
the examples and so on?
Good.
Oh yes, question.
When you say that the
model is always larger
than data set size, do you mean
one-to-one number of parameters
to number of tokens [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, that's a good question.
So the question
was something like,
What do I mean when I
say the model is larger
than the data set size?
What I mean is when the model
gets small relative to the data,
like you have way more data
than you have model size,
you enter this
irreducible error regime.
You basically fitted
the data as well
as you can for your
model class, and you
can't do any better no
matter how much data you add.
So we want to--
when we're thinking
about scaling laws,
we usually want to think about
this power law regime, which
is the simpler case.
Either that or you
explicitly fit the asymptote
and then you correct for it.
Those are the two things.
So when I say the model
is larger than the data,
it can be basically any amount
that is larger than the data,
as long as it's
in this power law
regime, usually like 10 times
bigger than the data, what
have you.
Cool.
Good.
OK, now we are back to
other data scaling laws.
So data scaling
laws by themselves
are not quite as useful
as you'd like them to be.
They just tell you how
fast does my model learn.
And that's kind of
useful for forecasting.
It's not useful
for very much else.
If you want to do
engineering, you
are probably interested
in other questions,
like what is my
optimal data mixture?
What is the best way for
me to pick my training
data for my model?
Very useful
engineering question.
Should I repeat my
data, or should I
just not repeat my data, save
the compute for something else?
Or maybe I should repeat
some high-quality stuff
and not repeat the
low-quality stuff.
I could do various other
things with repetition.
There's a lot of different
engineering decisions
I can make with data.
So how can scaling laws help us
make some of those decisions?
And I think one of the
things that's interesting
is if we think a little
bit about how classical
models behave.
Data scaling laws, if we
think about their origins
as essentially empirical
versions of generalization
bounds, they tell us, well, data
set composition for many models
really affect the offset
of these scaling laws,
but their slopes are actually
determined by the model class.
They're not really determined
by the distribution themselves.
So the slopes might
remain the same,
and only the intercepts
might change.
And the intercept might actually
be really interestingly shaped.
So this is a case of a toy
model with a linear regression
with two different things
you can sample from.
If you get only
one kind of data,
it's the errors are
high no matter what.
You actually want a
mixture of both right.
So if you write down how
this intercept behaves,
you actually start to get
some very interesting insights
about how having more data
diversity is very helpful.
But what does this
practically mean?
Well, practically
speaking, what this means
is you can actually fit data
scaling laws on mixtures,
and that can help
you do some data--
sorry, pre-training,
data optimization.
So what does this mean?
Let's say you have two data
sources for simplicity.
You have news, and
you have Wikipedia.
And how much news to use and
how much Wikipedia to use.
How can you determine that?
Well, you can train
really small models
on a really small
amount of data.
And then you can
basically train or you
can fit a function of how
different mixture levels affect
your performance.
You can do this while you scale
up your models little by little.
And you can see how
the trends change.
And you can try to extrapolate
that out the exact same way
as you would extrapolate
out a data scaling law.
And then you can ask
which one will be optimal
if I keep scaling it out
to my full training run.
So this is a very simple
idea of essentially fitting
a functional form at a
small amount of compute,
finding the minimum, and
then scaling that guy out.
So this is a data
mixing loss paper.
Unfortunately, I
think if you talk
to anyone who's done a lot
of these data mixture work,
they will tell you
reality is a lot more
noisy than this ideal
world would suggest.
And really, what has, as far as
I know, happened in many cases
is you end up training
a bunch of small models.
You pick the best data
mix from the small model,
and you just scale that guy
up, no scaling law required.
And data decide if you're
interested in this kind of thing
is a nice, large-scale empirical
study of these kinds of data
mixture things.
And what they
found was actually,
if you don't fit a scaling
law, and instead you
just pick the best data
mix at the small scale,
that works well.
For what it's worth, that's
consistent with the argument
that the intercepts differ,
but the slopes don't change.
Because if the
slopes don't change,
the best mixture at small
scale is also the best mixture
at large scale.
OK, another really
interesting set
of questions that I'll also
mention in the context of data
is repetition.
I think it's increasingly the
case that compute is growing,
the amount of data that
we have is not growing.
And so there's a lot
of people interested
in questions of what
happens when you repeat
data more and more times.
And there was a nice study a few
years back called "Scaling Data-
Constrained Language Models,"
where they roughly show
something like up to four epochs
with standard training recipes,
you just don't get hurt at all.
But if you go past that
point, then actually
your realized scaling
law, this dark curve
is much worse than the
projected scaling law
if you had fresh data.
That's the dashed
line over here.
And you can also, once again,
write down a modified functional
form that's generally predictive
of the behavior of this scaling
law under repetition.
And we can take this idea
even more to the extreme.
This was kind of
recent work with Percy
in one of our
co-advise students,
where we were asking,
like, OK, what
happens if you take
this idea to the extreme
and you just consider
infinite amounts of compute?
So you're allowed to epoch
as many times as you want,
like an infinite
amount of times.
What is the best thing that
you can get out of this system?
Well, it turns
out you can't just
keep repeating
passes over the data.
You can't keep making
your models bigger.
Those have diminishing returns.
And so you end up
reaching for other things,
like ensembling your models to
try to squeeze more and more
out of your data.
But really, I think the one
thing that I'll point out
that's really interesting
is your standard data
scaling laws here in the red.
It's a very nice, predictable,
improvement in performance
as you increase
the amount of data.
We do all sorts of interventions
like regularizing and adding
ensembles.
You get improvements
in performance,
but the slopes look actually
surprisingly similar.
This is a lesson
that you'll learn
once you start fitting your
own scaling laws, that very,
very often your
slopes don't change.
Often, the interventions
that you do just
change the intercept
of the scaling laws.
One last thing
that I'll mention,
because I like this paper
in the context of scaling
laws and scaling in
general, is that a lot
of the phenomena we
care about in data
is actually very
scale-dependent.
And one example of
this is data filtering.
So if you or I tomorrow
decide to filter some data
for the models we're
training, we would probably
filter very aggressively.
We would only keep the
highest quality stuff
because both you and I don't
have very much compute.
So we can't train on
all the internet anyway.
We might as well filter down
to the most high-quality stuff.
On the other hand, if you
have a lot of compute,
then you want to train
on more and more stuff
because you're going
to not want to repeat
on this very high-quality data.
So as you get more
and more compute,
your filter has become
looser and looser,
and potentially you
start training on stuff
that's lower and lower quality.
So a lot of the
things that we often
think about statically,
things like data
filtering or the
quality of data,
are actually much more dynamic.
As you increase scale,
you have to think about
where am I going to get
the rest of the data.
The filters can't stay fixed
as a function of the data,
and certainly the
optimal filters
turn out to not be fixed
at a function of scale.
OK, so that's it for
data scaling laws.
This is the part
that I think is most
straightforward to understand.
Even as a
stats/ML-minded person,
this stuff is all very simple
and straightforward to me.
You increase data,
performance gets better
in a very predictable way.
I think this is uncontroversial.
The fact that it does
so polynomially for such
a big model is still cool,
but nothing really crazy.
So hopefully this is
reasonable to all of you
that there's so much
predictability when you
increase the amount of data.
Oh, yes.
So on this slide
for the pre-training
under infinite compute,
so that graph on the right
is linear in both the
loss and data set size,
whereas the previous example
I gave was log-log scale.
And I was wondering why
it's linear in both.
Yeah, so this is a bad axis.
Herman and I just talked
about bad axis like this.
This is actually doubling.
So it looks linear, but
it's actually log scale.
[LAUGHS]
I fixed it now.
You fixed it now.
And the y-axis here,
it doesn't look logged,
but the range of
this is so small
that linear logs are
basically the same.
If you look at the fitted
functional forms here,
these are still polynomials.
So we're fitting the
same functional forms,
and those are the ones
that are plotted here.
This is another point.
I'll get to it at the
end of the lecture.
If you only have a tiny
slice of a compute range,
it's very, very
difficult to tell
if something is
scaling polynomially
or if something's
scaling exponentially.
Because Taylor
approximations are a thing.
Everything looks linear
if you zoom in enough.
And so whether
this is polynomial
or some other
functional form, you
want to be always a little
bit careful and skeptical.
Good.
OK.
All right, so that was
scaling laws for data,
in many ways straightforward.
Now I want to talk about
more exotic forms of scaling
and scaling laws for model
engineering of various kinds.
So what we're going
to do now is we're
going to try to design
large language models.
Maybe you're a radical, and
you believe that maybe LSTMs
are the future.
Like, why can't I use LSTM
instead of a transformer?
I want to blow my
B200 run on my LSTMs.
Or maybe you're a
different kind of radical
and you want to train on SGD.
Like, why can't I train on SGD?
You might also wonder.
If you have a limited
amount of resources,
you have different
ways to spend it.
Maybe you should
train models longer,
maybe you train
bigger models, maybe I
should go collect more data.
There's all sorts of
trade-offs always at play,
and scaling laws give us
quantitative ways of making
these trade-offs, hopefully.
I'm going to start off with
some simple hyperparameter
questions, things like how
do I choose my architecture
or optimizer, things
that I talked about
in the second lecture.
And there I gave you
the perspective of maybe
you can study what
other people do.
Now I'm going to try to give
you a first-principal answers
to those questions with a
little bit of a different set
of trade-offs.
So you have to believe in
scaling laws in this lecture,
but as long as you do, you
get to try things on your own
and find out.
OK, the very first question
we might start with is to say,
Are transformers really
better than LSTMs?
LSTMs.
They can work OK, too.
They will fit distributions.
With the advent of
things like Mamba,
we know that SSMS can work.
So are they better?
The brute force way to
answer this question
is to train a big LSTM GPT-3
or even bigger class of models.
The scaling law way would be to
train a bunch of smaller models
and say, I'm going to
train my transformer
across a different
variety of compute ranges,
and I'm going to train different
LSTMs with different numbers
of layers on, once
again, a variety
of different compute ranges.
Now, what does this show?
This shows LSTMs have definitely
different intercept, maybe even
different slope than
the transformer.
And because of this, probably
you don't want to pick out LSTM.
This plot would justify scaling
up the transformer instead
of the LSTM.
And if you look at a lot
of the architecture papers
today, like you go
look at the Mamba
paper or the gated
delta net papers,
they will always
have a plot that
looks like this, where you have
vanilla transformer, our really
cool model.
And our really cool models,
usually either on top or below,
because that's what would prove
that your model is doing better.
And you certainly don't want
something where your slopes are
worse because that means as
you scale up larger and larger,
your models will
eventually do worse.
So this is one way
of really reasoning
about architectures without
training gigantic models.
There haven't been,
I think, quite
as many recent and good
architecture scaling law papers.
I think the one that
is relatively recent
and that I like quite a lot
is by Ek and others at Google,
back when they were
publishing this kind of work,
where they did a whole bunch
of scaling studies on T5-style
models, where they trained
larger and larger variants of T5
models on many
different architectures.
And I think one thing
that's really cool,
and one of the reasons why
I still bring this paper up,
is they capture exactly
the architecture
changes that we implement
today in our frontier models.
So things like performer, which
is an efficient attention, that
doesn't scale very well.
We do not implement those.
The things that we implement
are the gated linear unit.
Red line better than green line
throughout the scaling trends.
Switch transformer.
I don't what happened
with their biggest run,
but generally speaking, it's
got good scaling trends.
And I forgot, oh,
mixture of softmaxes.
Actually, we don't
do this anymore,
but this is probably an
effective intervention
given the scaling trends.
So you see that through
this scaling trends,
even though a lot
of these papers
were operating on much,
much smaller compute scales
than what we operate
today, they're
able to see the kinds
of architecture trends
that are driving frontier
model development back then.
And I think this is why a lot
of people use scaling laws
as a really, almost
paradigmatic way, saying, "Oh,
if it doesn't show up
in the scaling law,
it's not a good intervention."
Because in some ways,
a lot of the past work
has captured what we see today.
Good.
OK, going beyond
architectures, we
can extend this kind of analysis
to all sorts of other things
that we might want
to understand.
We might ask, OK, is SGD
better or worse than ADAM?
If you do the scaling
law analysis, this one's
by Hestness, you'll
see very clear trends.
This is once again, the
really mysterious thing
of the intercepts are different,
but the slopes are very similar.
If you fix the data
and you fix the models,
slopes are often
very, very similar.
I am very surprised by
this every time I see it.
And yet, it's very true.
It's rare to get
different slopes,
even with an intervention
as big as SGD to ADAM.
If you were the one
training with SGD or ADAM,
you would think
that's a huge change.
Scaling trends remain
roughly the same.
In this case, this is
a language modeling
with a recurrent highway net.
Similarly, in lecture 2, I
told you about aspect ratios.
How do you pick your
depth-to-width trade-off?
And I told you,
well, you can just
pick some random number that's
somewhat roughly reasonable.
It's like four times the
reasonable multiplier.
But if you're doing this
kind of scaling analysis,
you could much more
precisely what is happening.
So the first thing
you could do is
you could look at scaling
trends as a function of layers,
and you would immediately see
that having extremely few layers
is very, very bad
for your model.
If you have one layer,
you're not going anywhere.
That's a terrible,
terrible scaling trend.
Greater than 1
layer, actually, it's
surprisingly more
competitive, although you
do see that at every compute
level, more layers, at least
in this case is better.
And if you can do a much more
fine-grained study, which
they do in Kaplan, where
you try to identify what
you might call
scale-invariant quantities,
like the aspect ratio.
The number of layers is not
a scale-invariant quantity.
As you make your model bigger,
you do want more layers.
But as you make
your model bigger,
maybe the aspect
ratio, the optimal one
should stay the same.
This one is scale invariant.
And so if we look
at the aspect ratio,
we see that at
different model sizes,
we get basically the same minima
around 100d model for every
layer, or maybe a
little bit less.
And it does shift
a little bit right.
There is a shift
towards aspect ratio
that is smaller for deeper
models, but for the most part,
the minima stays
roughly similar.
You can do similar
kinds of analysis
for things like attention
head dimension and others.
And if you look at
the Kaplan paper,
they do quite a good job
at doing all of this.
And this is one way that you can
be confident about your scaling
strategy.
So if your scaling strategy
is "I'm going to fix my aspect
ratio, and I'm
going to scale up,"
you can make plots like this and
convince yourself we're probably
good because our optimization
shifting too much as I go
to larger and larger
and larger models.
One thing that's important, and
this is a huge can of worms,
and a sufficiently
big can of worms
that I will talk about it
on more than one slide,
I will come back, not all
parameters are created equal.
And because not all
parameters are created equal,
your scaling laws
may look good or bad
depending on how you
define what a parameter is.
So in the Kaplan paper, they
made this observation that
if they drew their scaling laws
for depth with the embedding
parameters, they got these very
funky-looking scaling laws,
and they said, "Oh, this is no
good at all, no good at all."
Because it's no
good at all, they
decided that they
were going to exclude
all the embedding parameters,
and they were only
going to count the non-embedding
parameters because you could
justify it to
yourself, saying these
are the parameters that are
doing computation or whatever.
We're going to see
later that this
is going to have non-trivial
implications on the validity
of some of the results.
But the point here is
scaling laws aren't magic.
I think Percy likes
to make this point,
that scaling laws and all
these kinds of predictability
across scales is engineered.
They don't happen automatically.
We need to pick the right
kinds of x-axes to look at.
We need to make sure that the
hyperparameters for these things
are set right, and only
under those conditions
does it become possible
to get predictable scaling
across many orders
of magnitude compute.
So this is what a lot of
scaling law researchers do.
They think about
what the right way
is to get very
predictable scaling.
Now, related to
this, I think are
very interesting recent
papers on things like scaling
for mixture of experts.
Now, that mixture of
experts is, you would say,
the dominant way of
training large models,
it is quite important to
think about what is the value
or what is a parameter
in this new world
where the number of parameters
and the number of parameters
are kind of decoupled.
And there's a nice,
clean analysis
by some folks at
Apple and MIT that
show the scaling trends as a
function of both parameters
and active parameters.
And the cool thing
that you see is,
as you start to train
bigger and bigger models,
if you increase the
amount of total parameters
on the x-axis over here, and
you want to minimize your loss,
you're going to end up with
more sparse and sparse models.
See how the color becomes
darker and darker and darker.
Similarly, here, if you like
the number of active parameters
decreases as a function
of MoE sparsity.
And you get the
result that I think
is somewhat
intuitive here, which
is you can draw these surfaces.
For every compute
amount, you can ask, OK,
would I rather spend that
compute on active parameters
and how much sparsity do I want?
I can vary my sparsity without
really changing the amount
of compute that I'm spending.
Now, given that you
can ask, OK, what
happens if I add more
of empty parameters,
same active parameters,
but more total parameters?
As you move from
back on the plot
to in the front of the plot, you
see the losses are improving.
So in other words,
this is saying
that the parameters in an
MoE that are not active
are still helping you
reduce your loss, which
is kind of cool.
And you can write down what the
functional forms of this are.
I won't go into that
part in more detail,
but the point here is to say
all of these kinds of quantities
that we care about
in optimizing MoE
are things that have predictable
scaling and regularities.
And the two things I want to now
talk about are actually really--
yeah, two things that I
now want to talk about.
When you're going to
train a new big model,
actually, most of the things
that I talk about are fixed.
You're probably all
not radical enough
that you're going
to switch to a LSTM.
You're probably going to
pick like, I don't know,
a DeepSeek-V4-inspired
MoE or something.
And you're probably going to
pick architecture choices that
are tried and tested.
You're not going to really
throw everything out.
But two things
that you really do
have to maybe
reinvent in some sense
is the batch size and
the learning rate.
If you train your
deep learning models,
you know that you have
to be very careful
about the combination of your
batch size and learning rate.
You change one, you have
to change the other.
Now, batch size, from
the previous lecture,
is very tricky for
another reason.
We want the batch size
to be as big as possible
because a big batch size
gives us opportunity
for parallelization.
Remember, data parallel
requires large batch size.
So now, having said all
that, what we really want to
is how large can we
make our batch size
before we start to suffer?
That's the relevant
systems question.
And you also want to
how does that change
as a function of model size.
So given that preface, there
is this very important idea
that is used in a
variety of papers
and talked about
very frequently,
called the critical batch size.
The critical batch size
is roughly this idea that
up until a certain
point, when you
start to get
diminishing returns,
there is returns,
perfect returns,
to increased batch size.
So I might call this the
noise-limited regime.
So in the noise-limited regime,
every additional element
that you throw in your batch
reduces the gradient noise
in your SGD step.
And since you're
variance-limited,
that reduction in variance
is very, very helpful.
That gives you big returns.
So this is the regime in which
you have perfect scaling.
You're doing about
as well as you can,
given the amount of extra
examples that you're processing.
As you get to a
certain point where
you've reached the noise
scale of your gradients,
you get to a point where you
are no longer variance-limited.
You're now bias-limited.
What does that mean?
Well, remember, in
gradient descent,
you're looking at the local
structure of your objective.
You don't have a global view
of where the minimum is.
So no matter how
low noise I am, I'm
only going to point in this
light blue direction over here.
And there's always
a disagreement
between my local
descent direction
and where the global optimum is.
Because of that,
at a certain point,
I'm going to get
diminishing returns
because now my limiting
factor is no longer variance.
It is this bias term.
So now I'm bias-limited
past this point over here.
And so critical batch is
kind of a rule of thumb,
you might call it, or a
convenient trade-off point where
you say this is the point
at which we're starting
to cross over from
our perfect scaling
regime to our ineffective
scaling regime.
And so it gives you
a good rule of thumb
of where to be setting
your batch size if you want
your batch size to be as big
as possible without suffering
these huge efficiency losses.
Hopefully, that
idea is very clear.
Now, critical batch size is
kind of a strange object.
It is derived from a variety
of complicated calculations
about the local quadratic
approximations to the objective.
But I will maybe give
you the mechanical steps
of what is actually used
to estimate this quantity.
So what you do is first,
you pick a target loss.
Target loss might be some
numbers that you want to hit.
So your goal is to
hit this target loss
as quickly as possible.
That's my goal right now.
What I'm going to do
is I'm going to sweep
over all the different
batch sizes or number
of different batch
sizes, and I'm
going to write down the
number of steps that I needed
to reach my target loss,
and the number of examples
that were needed to get
to that target loss.
Of course, number
one and two are
related by a batch size factor.
The number of steps
times my batch size
is equal to the
number of examples.
Now, through some calculations,
OpenAI folks, McCandless
and others, argue that this
is the rough functional form
that we should follow, that the
number of steps that you need
and the number of
examples that you need
are inversely related,
with this estimate, which
is the minimum number
of possible steps
and the minimum
number of examples,
normalizing these
two quantities.
And so there's a trade-off
between these two.
If you want to minimize
the number of examples,
you're going to
have a lot of steps.
And if you want to minimize
the number of steps,
you're going to need
a lot of examples.
That's a very natural trade-off.
And if you increase or
decrease your batch size,
you're going to have trade-offs
that go one side or the other.
Now, they argue
the goal now should
be to balance these two sides.
I want to make sure that
my number of steps term
and the number of
examples terms are roughly
balanced with each other.
And if you solve
for that, you're
going to get this
particular solution, which
is that the critical
batch size is
the minimum number
of examples that I
need divided by the minimum
number of steps that I need.
And these two are estimated by
fitting this to the observed
data that I have.
This is going to balance
both sides of the equation.
It's going to give me a little
bit more number of steps
than optimal.
It's going to require a little
bit more examples than optimal,
but it balances the two sides.
And you can think of this as
optimizing the convergence rate
without blowing up the number
of steps that you need.
There's another added
point that I won't really
belabor because this gets
even more into the weeds.
You should really read the
critical batch size paper
if you're interested into this,
where one of their arguments
is estimating this
is quite complicated.
You can do this by just
looking at the ratio
of the gradient covariance
in the squared norm
of your gradient.
So why is that even in
the scaling lecture?
This is a thing that
is not really related
to scaling so far.
The reason why this is
in the scaling lecture
is because, first of all,
the critical batch size
is a reasonable
batch size to pick.
That's a batch size that
balances convergence rate
and the size of the batch.
So if I want to pick my batch
size equal to my critical batch
size, you might ask,
how does this thing
scale as a function
of my target loss?
Target loss can be
thought of as compute.
If I want to have a model that
is better and better and better,
what is the batch size
that I should use?
And the reason why this
isn't the scaling law lecture
is as you go down in scale
in the loss, so your loss is
improving, the amount of
critical batch size increases.
And it increases in this
very predictable way, which
is once again, a power law.
So this is the relationship
that they argue,
which is roughly inverse
polynomial in batch size.
So given this, this
is actually quite nice
because what this is
saying is if you have
a really large-scale
training run where you go all
the way to the
right of this plot,
your batch sizes
can be quite large.
And that makes sense.
As you get closer and closer
and closer to the minimum,
the value of variance
reduction increases.
Because you're trying to
optimize finer and finer
and finer grained
objects, the noise
matters a lot more once you're
minimizing really, really
tiny differences.
So that's the batch size story.
The other side-- so
the two quantities,
remember, that you're going
to always have to tune
is batch size and learning rate.
The learning rate
side of the story
is also a little
bit complicated.
I'll go into this much more
detail in the advanced scaling
lecture.
But learning rates
generally shift.
I think this is a good
mental picture for how
to think about learning
rates in the standard world
that you start with,
which is, let's say,
that you have just like a MLP.
Just a standard neural
network of some kind.
I'm not going to
do depth scaling.
I'm only going to
do width scaling.
Now, if I'm doing width
scaling, the bigger
my model, the bigger
my model, the smaller
my learning rate should be.
And the reason why my learning
rate should be smaller
is because I have
bigger, more parameters,
I'm changing more
things at once.
Maybe I should move less.
It kind of makes sense.
And in fact, there's
a rule of thumb
that maybe you want to
scale by 1 over the width.
That's a very commonly
known rule of thumb
that you want to just decrease
the learning rate regularly
as a function of
your width, and that
will give you a rule of thumb
to scale your learning rate.
There is another
school of thought,
or another set of
tricks that people do,
which is that
people also rescale
the network in various ways.
They will change the
initialization sizes,
and they will change
the step sizes
of the optimizer for
various parts of the network
in order to force the model
to have the same learning rate
minimum across scales.
And this is an idea that is
called mu p and others like it.
Some people have
reported great success
with these kinds of
approaches, others
have reported less success.
The two ways, basically,
of setting a learning rate
for large-scale runs really
is captured in this plot.
In one way, you
can try to estimate
what these minima are
and try to predict
what your minimum will be.
And the way in which the minimum
changes is pretty predictable,
so this is not a crazy idea.
Or you can
reparameterize your model
to try to keep the learning
rate minimum the same,
and then just pick your
best learning rate and go.
Those are the two philosophies
to picking your learning rate.
Both of them have been
applied successfully at scale.
There are large-scale
training runs
that have used both approaches.
I think anecdotally it does seem
more people are maybe favoring
the scaling law approach,
but both are certainly
viable approaches.
I'll talk in detail about
both of these next lecture.
So before I get into the
last part of this lecture,
where I want to
talk about not quite
pitfalls but various details
of scaling law things,
one thing I want to
end this section with
is the idea that upstream
and downstream performance
can be quite different.
So if you look at something
like log likelihood,
this is from the Yi Tay
architectures paper,
you find that perplexity and
negative perplexity in this case
parameters are very correlated.
The more parameters you
have, the better your model,
very predictably.
This is a very
beautiful linear trend.
Now you're like,
OK, this is great.
Now we're going to
ship our best model.
NL12.
Turns out NL12 is
not your best model.
It was actually NL32XL,
which was a much worse model
in perplexity.
This is a very common
thing that does happen.
Upstream and downstream
are often correlated.
This is probably one of
the worst correlations
that I've seen from
upstream to downstream.
But I think it's
very, very important
to remember that scaling laws,
generally speaking, are objects
that you want to apply
on the perplexity side.
They're very clean,
they're very regular,
they're very predictable.
But transfer from
perplexity to downstream
is a lot less certain than
it might initially seem.
This is a place where you
want to be very cautious.
And as an anecdote, I
have former students
that have gone and done
post-training of various places,
and they always complain.
They're like, "Oh, those
pre-training people,
they hand you this model.
They are like, the
perplexity is good.
It's all your problem now."
But it's often the
problems have started
at the pre-training side.
So you don't want to
be one of those people.
You want to really think
about transfer as well,
not just focus on perplexities.
OK, so maybe this is
surprising, maybe this is not.
But the point that I
want to drill in here
is that before you do
your big training run,
you should have a rough idea
of what you're going to see.
Not just is it going
to train at all.
In fact, if you do
scaling laws, you
should be able to actually
predict fairly precisely
the numerical values,
almost, of how good
your run is going to be.
If I choose one optimizer
versus the other,
what will the gain be?
You should be able
to predict that.
So the scaling
law-based procedure
is to say I'm going to train
a bunch of smaller models,
I'm going to establish
some of a scaling law
by fitting these lines
onto log-log plots.
And then if the
fit is good enough,
I'm going to have some
confidence that the gap will
persist, and then I'm
just going to deploy that
onto my large-scale
training run.
This is the naive version
of a scaling law procedure,
but I think one
that is reasonably
accurate for how you might think
about these things in practice.
What else are you going to do?
Just deploy a run
out of nowhere?
Probably not.
OK, I can pause here
and take some questions
before I get into the
last part of this lecture.
Yes.
For each of the data
points on the scaling law,
how do you think about variance?
How many runs do you do?
And is aggregation
usually like the average,
or do you take min or max
depending on [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, I think in most cases, if
not all cases that I've seen,
those are singletons.
And the reason why
it's a singleton
is because when you're
looking at perplexities,
perplexities are
very, very clean.
These objects, if
you rerun them,
they're probably
like the variances
in the second decimal
place or something
because the training
data is very
homogeneous, you've got a lot of
it, your eval sets are very big.
You've really pushed the
variance very, very low
on these things.
But if you're doing something
learning rate or critical batch
size scaling laws, you will see
some truly horrendous stuff.
I do think people do
some variance reduction,
but it's actually not
that common as common
as it should be, maybe.
Yes.
Do people use just
downstream metrics directly
instead of using perplexity?
Yeah, people do scaling laws
directly on downstream metrics,
but that has the
same problem as this.
So I think the way to
think about scaling laws
is to really reliably
establish at least one thing.
So the way to think
about it is, let's say
I see something
like this, I have
a strong belief that
this transformer
line is going to continue.
This is a very regular trend.
And it might curve
a little bit, but we
do think there's probably
some regularity here.
But instead, imagine this
was a very noisy jaggedy line
of this form.
You would not really
know what is going on.
You would say, I maybe
believe that it will go on,
but maybe it's a line,
maybe it's a curve.
So I think the general--
if I'm trying to explain the
philosophy of this stuff,
is to say, OK, let's start with
the low variance measurement
and then establish scaling
regularity there and then rely
on some of belief about
transfer or establish transfer
or elsewhere to try to show
that would transfer over
to downstream.
Yeah.
So some of these
are [INAUDIBLE],
and some are just
[INAUDIBLE] loss.
When do you do either?
I see, yes.
You fit to test loss when you're
doing good scientific practice,
like Kaplan 2021.
But realistically, all the
models, except for a very few,
like the infinite compute
one and the repetition stuff,
unless you're doing some of
that, you're doing one-pass SGD.
So the generalization gap
for all of these models
is very, very small.
So train and val
are very similar.
I've seen some pre-training
code bases that don't even
have validation loss.
Because if you're doing
one pass, most likely
your train and val
are very, very close.
That's why a lot of these
plots exchange those two,
because they're all in
the one-pass regime.
Good question, though.
OK, all right, we will
continue to move on to--
sorry, I moved on too
far backwards here.
OK, so now I'm going
to talk about one
of the most well-known
uses of a scaling law.
Even though you might not
personally be using this,
you've certainly used the
rule of thumb at some point.
And also, I think because
this set of things
will tell us something really
interesting about the actual
execution of a scaling law.
OK, the motivating
question is, do I
want more data or bigger models?
So the resource that
you have, the resource
that you have to
spend, is compute.
Someone's going to hand you
metaphorically a certain amount
of FLOPs.
And you're going to
take those FLOPs,
and you're going to
spend them somehow
on-- if you remember Percy's
very first lecture, it's
going to be data times
the parameters is roughly
your FLOPs, linear in that.
So do I want more
data or more models?
Well, we know that if we
take a teeny tiny model
and we dump tons of data into
it, that will just be wasted.
That's the dark purple
line at the very top here.
I've taken a teeny
tiny language model,
and I've passed a huge
amount of data into it,
and this thing has been
flat for a very long time.
This is a complete
waste of compute.
You would have much rather
trained this big yellow model
to the same amount of
tokens or even earlier
on, if you're having the
same amount of compute.
Now, if you could understand
the interaction of how
data amount and model size
come together to give you
performance, if you
understood that relationship,
you could optimize
this very precisely.
And so there are scaling
laws that are more advanced
and relate kind of joint
behaviors of objects.
So almost simultaneously,
Kaplan and Rosenfeld
both proposed these
functional forms,
which are roughly
equivalent, describing
how the size of the model
and the amount of data
relate to the error.
Rosenfeld is very simple.
It's really just the sum
of two inverse terms.
These are two scaling laws
that are added together.
And Kaplan is a little
bit more complicated,
but it's roughly the same idea.
And if you look at,
think about the limits,
this is very intuitive.
If I have an infinite amount
of data, then what happens?
Then this goes to 0.
You're basically
model-size limited.
You become a pure
model size scaling law.
If I send my model
size to infinity,
then I'm going to
be bounded by data.
I'm going to have a
pure data scaling law.
So it makes sense if you take
the limits of both of these.
It's often a good idea if
someone tells you a scaling law
to take the limits
of all the variables
to understand the
behavior of the system.
Now, the thing
that's kind of cool
is Rosenfeld and
many others that
have proposed these kinds
of joint scaling laws
show that these things fit quite
well, even if you extrapolate.
So what you're going
to do is you're
going to fit on these green
points, which is a low compute
regime and low data regime.
You never see things that have
either high data or high model
sizes.
And then you can
extrapolate on the basis
of these tiny runs in
this corner over here
to essentially this high compute
or high data, high model size
regime.
And you can very accurately
predict the error
based on your predictions.
Great predictions.
And so once you have that,
now what you can do is to say,
well, I have a fixed amount
of FLOPs subject to my FLOPs
constraints, minimize this.
That's a simple nonlinear
optimization problem.
You can do that
to solve for this.
Now, both Kaplan and Rosenfeld
provide equations of this form.
What do they say?
Well, if you look at Kaplan, and
they solve for this equation,
they say something like this.
Well, the amount of--
they always flip this.
It confuses me.
The amount of data it
should be C to the 0.73,
and the amount of model size
should be C to the 0.27.
Is that reversed?
I think it's reversed, sorry.
N should be the
amount of parameters
and D should be
the amount of data.
And so tokens per
parameters decreases with C.
So as you increase
the compute amounts,
this prescription
by Kaplan tells
you to train bigger and
bigger and bigger models.
And so if you were around
in the days of GPT-3,
it kind of shocks me
to think that there
are people who
were not, you would
know that there was a
period where everyone was
training these gigantic models.
Like hundreds of
billions of parameters
of models, trillion-parameter
dense models, what have you.
And part of that
was driven by this.
They saw GPT-3, they saw
these Kaplan predictions,
and they said, "Wow, I'm going
to do my big training runs
on these gigantic
model size models."
But a few years later, in 2022,
some folks at DeepMind, Hoffman
et al., came in and they
said, well, actually,
these predictions
are all terribly off.
You've been training these
giant models, these three
stars over here, but actually,
those are way too big.
What we should be
training instead
is a very different trend, this
line on the blue over here,
and we should be training
this teal star, which
is a much better model.
So they argued that we should
be training much smaller models
relative to this.
And I think, of
course, many of you
or all of you probably
the Chinchilla paper,
you know what the
token multipliers are.
It's 20 tokens to
every parameter.
But I think this is
useful to go in detail
because the Chinchilla-Kaplan
disagreement and all of this
tells us something important
about how we should
be thinking about scaling laws.
It's not just something
where you turn the crank,
and you get the answer.
It's something that's actually
careful and sensitive,
and we have to
respect the process.
So I'm going to walk through
the Chinchilla paper.
And after I walk through
the Chinchilla paper,
I'm going to talk about why
the Kaplan and Chinchilla
papers disagree and
what that means for you.
So the Chinchilla author
suggests three different ways
of fitting scaling laws.
I really like this because it's
a way of robustifying yourself
to modeling assumptions
you may have made.
And each of these actually
is quite a different approach
to estimating the trade-off
between model size and data.
And minus method 3, which
does differ a little bit,
they mostly agree.
All 1 and 2 both agree
that the coefficients
for data and for model
size are roughly the same.
0.5, 0.5, 0.49, 0.51.
Method 3 does differ, 0.46 and
0.54, but we'll talk about why
later.
Kaplan et al., of course,
have a very big difference
between the two, which is why
they were training big models
at big, big compute sizes.
Method number 1
from Chinchilla is
what I might call the
lower envelope method.
And this is the method that
was also being used partially
by Kaplan to try to figure out
what the right scaling was.
And so what you do is you take
all of your training runs.
So each one of these colored
lines is a training curve.
And what you want
to do is you want
to actually take the lower
envelope of these training
curves.
Because a lower envelope
point on this training curve,
that means that for
a particular FLOP,
this is the best loss that I
ever achieved for that FLOP
on any training run.
So I can take all of
the lower envelope
points at the very bottom here
at the high compute regime,
and then I can plot
all those points
to see how big were the models
that each of these FLOP points
intersected.
Because each of these
points is a training
run with a model size.
And if I scatter plot that, I
will get a nice linear trend.
And that will give me one way of
estimating the optimal trade-off
between FLOP to parameters.
And that gives one answer, which
is for their compute budget,
they should train a 67
billion parameter model.
This is a nice and simple way,
but very tricky defining things
like what is the lower envelope,
and so on and so forth.
There's definitely
some tricky parts.
Method 2 is IsoFLOP.
This is now very popular.
It's also very easy
and very robust.
This is probably my
personal favorite method.
And what you do
is, for this, you
pick a bunch of
different FLOPS budgets.
So I have a different range of
FLOPS budgets going in factors
of 3 in this case or 1, 3, 6.
And what you do is
for each FLOP budget,
you're going to essentially
sweep the space.
So here I have one
variable, which
is the parameter-to-data
trade-off.
So for each FLOP
budget, I'm going
to sweep over the parameter to
data trade-off, fixing my FLOPS.
So I double my data size,
I half my model size,
so on and so forth.
And that will generate a
sequence of training runs
whose terminal loss is going
to sweep out some of curve.
So each one of these
colored sets of points
is a fixed FLOP run.
Each point is sweeping
across different parameters,
and of course, it's implicitly
sweeping over data as well.
Now, the nice thing now is I
can take the minimum over each
of these runs, or
even fit a quadratic
and take the minimum
over the quadratics,
and then I can draw
a line through all
of the bottoms of
the quadratics,
or take the bottom
of the quadratics
and plot them as a function
of FLOPS to parameters.
And that will give me
another prediction,
which agrees very closely.
These is $63 billion parameters
for my compute budget.
Now, the final
approach that we can do
is actually the maybe
most natural one,
as suggested by the Rosenfeld
paper as well as the Kaplan
paper, because both
of them are propose
a hypothesized functional
form for how model
size and data relate to loss.
So if you have such a joint
functional form, what you can do
is you can take a whole bunch of
training runs that you've done,
and you can fit your
loss landscape, which
is your hypothesized
functional form,
and you can just
do curve fitting
to estimate what the
coefficients are in your scaling
law.
This is the most
brute-force way.
You have a hypothesized
relationship
between loss, data
size, and model size
train a bunch of models,
do curve fitting.
Hopefully, fairly
straightforward--
how you do that.
Of course, if you're doing
this method, how you do
the curve fitting
is very important.
Now, you're fitting
these surfaces,
there's many variables,
it's kind of tricky.
This thing also has some
trickiness, just like method 1.
So it's not a straightforward
way the same way
that maybe FLOPS is.
So now that we've gone
through what Chinchilla does,
it doesn't seem materially
different than what
Kaplan was doing.
It's not like Kaplan was
doing one crazy thing and then
the Chinchilla authors did
something way smarter and you
said, "Wow, why didn't we
do that from the start?"
They both did pretty
reasonable stuff.
But if we look at their
scaling predictions,
they are very different.
And in hindsight, we generally
tend to agree with the fact
that the Chinchilla authors had
more of the correct scaling.
If you do your own
Chinchilla-style analysis,
you will find probably scaling
is much closer to Chinchilla.
Now, so why is there such
a big difference when
they're both fitting
these joint scaling laws?
OK, so this is,
I think, where we
get into the messy realities
of how scaling laws are made.
Scaling laws can
really change depending
on the precise ways in which
you're implementing the scaling
laws, the hyperparameter
settings that you're using,
and even what the x-axis is.
So there's a really nice paper.
Oh, no, I covered the authors.
I can paste this in the
lecture Slack later.
--called "Resolving Discrepancy
to Compute-Optimal Scaling
of Language Models."
Yair is the last author.
He was a former student here.
And they show--
basically, first they
replicate the
Kaplan result using
roughly the Kaplan settings.
And then they say,
OK, well, let's
change how we count parameters.
That shifts the
curve a little bit.
And then they say,
OK, well, let's
change how learning
rate warmup is done.
That shifts the
curve a little bit.
And then let's tune the
optimizer a little bit more.
And then they get exactly
the Chinchilla result.
So their argument
here is that there
is a sequence of what seems very
minor decisions that in the end,
gives you this big gap
between the Kaplan scaling
law and the Chinchilla
scaling law.
And I'll explain what
each of these steps
is, not that that's the
most important single thing,
but also to emphasize to you how
important the details are here.
So the very first arrow,
where we go from Kaplan
to the blue line, that is
how we count parameters.
So remember, in
Kaplan, I said, well,
they saw this
weird stuff if they
included embedding parameters.
So they excluded
embedding parameters.
That's generally
an OK thing to do.
But one thing they also did
that really messed them up
was they also excluded
the last layer parameter
counts, the softmax ones.
Because in many models, the
embedding and the last layer
linear are dual to each other.
They have the same shapes.
The inside has vocab
size by hidden dim.
The output matrix has
hidden dim by vocab size.
And because they're
the same shape,
they said, well, let's
just exclude both of those.
It turns out whether
you include or exclude
those has a big material impact
on the shape of the scaling law.
They also found-- this is
much more of an oversight,
more than a genuine
difference in opinion,
that a lot of the models that
were being trained in Kaplan
were very small.
And in fact, they were so small
that they were not actually
converging by the time that the
learning rate warm up was done.
So their learning rates
were set very suboptimally.
And because of that, their
models weren't fully converged.
And then finally, they found
that Kaplan et al. was fixing
one big batch size, and
those big batch sizes
were suboptimal for
the smaller models.
And therefore, if you
tune that correctly
and you use varying
batch sizes, you
end up getting this thing that
agrees exactly with Chinchilla.
So I think each of
these might seem
like a very minor difference,
but if you change up
these really minor
differences, you
can get big shifts
in the scaling law.
And one thing I
like to emphasize
is that scaling laws are
lower bounds in some sense.
They're kind of saying,
if I continue this recipe
and I scale it up, then
this is what I will get.
But if you're scaling up a
recipe that you don't want
to scale up, your
warmup is kind of crazy,
or your batch sizes
are crazy, you're
going to get bad scaling laws.
So you want to be as close to
the proper full run as possible.
There's another paper that does
another very interesting thing
to try to study the difference
between Kaplan and Chinchilla
scaling laws.
It's by Pearce and Song.
And what they do, and I
think this is very clever,
is they don't train any models.
They just take the
Chinchilla training
curves or the implied functional
form of the Chinchilla training
curves.
They just plot them
out and they say, well,
based on these implied
training curves, which
are simulated purely
from Chinchilla,
they generate what the
implied training curves will
be for Kaplan if you ignore
the embedding parameters
and you scale way
down, and what happens
if you use the total
parameter count instead.
And what they find is
really two effects.
One is that Kaplan is operating
at a much lower compute scale,
so they're very sensitive
to small changes,
and actually ignoring the
non-embedding parameter
is a sufficiently big change
to mess up the result relative
to Chinchilla.
So their argument is slightly
different from Yair and others,
which is that here,
actually, it's
the size of the compute scale
plus the slight non-linearity
induced by non embedding
parameters that's
causing this disagreement.
So this is really starting
to get into the weeds.
But I hope you
appreciate the importance
of paying attention to detail.
And I think a lot of
the work that goes on
in establishing,
relying, scaling laws
is about figuring out
what the right regime is
so that you can get reliable
scaling across compute scales.
The final thing, and this is
really just more of something
that I just find amusing more
than anything else, which
is that Chinchilla is
this paper that takes down
the Kaplan paper in a way.
It's like, oh, you
guys were very wrong.
But there was this
one remaining mystery,
which is that Chinchilla
method three never agreed
with Chinchilla method 1 and 2.
And the numbers look small.
And the authors are very
unperturbed about this,
but I think the implications
are quite non-trivial.
If you look at this,
methods 1 and 2 basically
say the amount of parameters and
tokens should scale together.
So there should be a fixed
ratio between the two.
This is where the Chinchilla
factor of 20 comes from.
If you look at number 3,
the exponents are different.
This means if you
scale up your compute,
eventually, actually,
in this case,
you're going to have
way more tokens than you
are going to have parameters.
So it's going to be actually
a very different scaling
conclusion asymptotically
than the other ones.
And so it turns out that I was
certainly not the only one who
was perturbed about this,
except some folks at Epoch AI
did something about
being perturbed.
They couldn't get either
the raw data or the code.
So what they did was they
extracted the data from plots
in the paper, and they refitted
the method 3 regressions.
They extracted the
data from the paper.
And given that data, they fitted
that 2D surface or 3D surface
that was proposed.
And then, what they
showed is actually
the original paper must have
underfitted the original data.
And if they redid
the curve fitting,
they could get much lower
losses relative to what
the proposed scaling law
in the Chinchilla paper.
And in fact, if you
follow the refitted model,
you got almost
exactly D over 20 is
20 rule of thumb from
the Chinchilla paper,
which is really a
funny conclusion,
I think, to the Chinchilla
paper, where in the end
it turns out that the authors
were more right than they knew.
Actually, they had
made a mistake,
and that was the only reason
why method 3 disagreed
from methods 1 and 2.
So it's a nice conclusion
to know that the method was
robust after all.
OK, so that's the end of the
Chinchilla saga in some ways.
But I will end this section
by saying you probably don't
want the Chinchilla factor.
At this point, I think this is
a pretty common knowledge thing.
But if you're training
a production model,
you don't really care about
saving training compute
for the most part.
You can look at all
sorts of external surveys
that people have done
of how Frontier Labs are
spending their compute.
Most of the compute is not
going into training runs.
Most of the compute is actually
going into R&D and serving.
And given that, especially for
serving, what you want to do
is you want small
models that are capable.
You do not want big, bloated
models that cost a lot to serve,
even if that minimizes
training cost.
And so what you really want is
something that you would call
as "overtrained."
I put that in quotes
because, really, overtraining
is what we want.
That's the right
amount of training.
And if you look at all the
models that were released
in the early days, like GPT-3--
this was under-trained for sure,
three tokens per parameter.
Chinchilla gets to the modern
ratio of 20 per parameter.
And then for a while, people
were at 20 per parameter.
And this is the
era, I think, where
there wasn't that much
serving of these models.
The models were cool, but it
wasn't being served at scale.
And then as you start to move to
eras where serving becomes very
real, now you're
overtraining these models,
and now you've moved
into MoEs, and you're
making all these trade-offs
to optimize inference serving.
So I think Chinchilla
is important,
not because I think the 20-to-1
ratio is the one golden ratio.
If you're doing stuff for
research, it might be.
But I think the reason
why it's important
is because it tells us
quite a bit about how
we should be
fitting scaling laws
and how to think
about scaling laws.
OK, one final thing I'll
end with Chinchilla-wise
and otherwise for
scaling is IsoFLOP
have been one of the
things that, I think,
has a research
tool have endured.
IsoFLOP are very
easy to execute.
You fix a FLOPS
budget, and then you
sweep over all of the
other degrees of freedom
to see what the
surface looks like.
And this gives you, in general,
fairly reliable readings
of how different parameters
vary as a function
of your free parameters.
People have done this for-- or
actually, one of my students
did this for diffusion models.
The MoE study I talked about
was a IsoFLOP-style design.
If you're ever in a situation
where you're thinking,
how am I going to decide
all these trade-offs,
IsoFLOP is always
a good default.
OK, so to wrap up
everything for today,
there's this idea that we have
this log-linear regularity
between the amount of
resources we put in
and the performance we get out.
And it extends to a wide variety
of things, model parameters,
compute, sparsity
level of your MoE.
And that lets you do
a lot of the things
that I was talking about
earlier, as arbitrary choices,
but do it in a much more
evidence-driven way, hopefully.
And so this allows us to
have engineering at scale
without explicitly relying on
doing big model training runs.
And hopefully, you
remember, I think all
the different components here.
Data scaling is this
very natural object,
just the exponent is
a little bit strange.
Model scaling allows you to
do all these cool engineering
things.
And then finally, scaling
is this very cool,
robust predictor,
let's call it, for how
to try to do engineering
at a large scale.
And thanks.
The next lecture, I think,
will be Percy on inference.
But after that, we will return
to more advanced niche scaling
topics.
[APPLAUSE]